Guide to the Vassar College Africana Studies Records, 1969-2004
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Africana Studies Records
1969-2004
Vassar College. Africana Studies Program
11 cubic feet (11 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection consists of administrative records of the Africana Studies Program, primarily correspondence and subject files.
Administrative History
With recommendations and urging from the Vassar College Students’ Afro-American Society (SAS), a multidisciplinary program in Black Studies was approved in February, 1969. The Urban Black Studies Center was also established and opened off-campus that year to provided educational opportunities for Poughkeepsie residents. Both initiatives were considered experimental and not assured of permanent funding.
In 1975, the program was renamed as the Africana Studies Program. The Urban Center was closed in 1981, its funding shifted toward an endowment for Third World Studies.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of administrative records of the foundation and early development of the Africana Studies Program. Of particular note are the faculty meeting minutes and program chair's files. In addition to the standard records, there are two photograph albums and additional envelopes of photo prints from the 1971 study trip to Africa.
Access
There are three boxes of material that are restricted for reasons of personnel privacy as well as FERPA. The rest of the collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library.
Related Materials
Lawrence H. Mamiya Papers
Vassar College 1969 Black Studies Sit-in Records
Vassar College Office of the President Records, Alan Simpson Files
Subject Headings
Names:
Fierce, Milfred C., 1937-; Mamiya, Lawrence H.
Organizations:
Vassar College--Students; Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Africa--Study and teaching; African American students; African Americans--Study and teaching (Higher)--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Document Types:
Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs; Printed ephemera; Reports
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Academic Departments and Programs
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, November 2019. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, December 2024.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred in two accessions. The date of the first accession is unknown. Six boxes were transferred in 2013. [A2013-027]
Series List
- Series I. General Program Files, 1973-2004
- Series II. Subject Files, 1971-2004
- Series III. Lectures and Events, 1975-2004
- Series IV. Student and Personnel Records, undated; [RESTRICTED]
Container List
- Series I. General Program Files
  - Annual reports (incomplete set), 1977-2004; (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - Program reviews and reports, 1975, 1978, 1988; (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Faculty Committee on Black Studies, 1974-1975; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Trustee Committee on Minority Affairs, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Faculty correspondence, 1990-1992; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Faculty evaluation by students, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty forums, 1980-1981, 1985-1988; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Faculty handbook, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Faculty meetings (incomplete set), 1973-2003; (15 folders) (Box 1)
  - Faculty memos, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty recruitment, 1974-1987; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Faculty retreats, 1980-1992; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Program chairs' files, 1974-1982; (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - Program chairs' files, 1985-1992; (16 folders) (Box 2)
- Series II. Subject Files
  - AAAVC (African-American Alumnae/i of Vassar College) (Box 2)
  - Admissions, 1974-1978, 1986; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Advisor to Minority Students, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Advisers (pre-major), 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Affirmative action, 1976-1986; (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Africana Studies Committee on Cultural Affairs and Student Forum, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Africana Studies handbook, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Africana Studies majors, 1974-1988, 2003-2004; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Africana Studies Majors Committee, 1985-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - American Culture Program, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Arabic Studies, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Area Studies, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Audiovisual resources, 1977-1987; (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Black college exchange, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Black conferences, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Black drama workshop, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Black faculty caucus, 1980-1981, 1988-1990, 1998; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees - Salary freeze, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Bracketing courses, undated (Box 2)
  - Budget files, 1977-1983; (10 folders) (Box 2)
  - Budget files, 1985-2004; (19 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bulletin board, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Career Development, 1987-1989; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Catalog copy (Registrar), 1974-1989; (10 folders) (Box 3)
  - Catalog retrospective, 2002; (2 binders) (Box 8)
  - Coalition of Concerned Students and Faculty, 1990 Jan 26 (Box 3)
  - College Course, undated (Box 3)
  - Committee on Curricular Policies (CCP), 1974-2004; (12 folders) (Box 3)
  - Committee on the Education of Minority Students Report, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Community Leaders Directory, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Conferences, undated (Box 3)
  - Copyright, 1978, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Correlate sequence, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Course listings and schedules, 1974-2004; (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Dean of the College, 1985-1990; (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Dean of Freshman - Pat Kaurouma, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Dean of Student Life, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Dean of Studies, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - Development Office, undated (Box 4)
  - Educational Services and Student Relations (Office of), 1975; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Exploring Transfer Program, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Faculty Appointments and Salary Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Faculty bulletin board information, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Faculty-Freshman Dialogue, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Faculty leaves and replacements, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty meetings (general college), undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty review process, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty staffing plans, 2000-2004 (Box 4)
  - Faculty teaching schedules, 1981-1991; (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Faculty tenure, reappointment and promotion, 1975, 1978; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Faculty travel, 1974-1989; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Bickerstaff, Joyce, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Cottingham, Clement, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Hill, Anthony, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Hodges, Norman, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Lynch, Hollis, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Mamiya, Lawrence, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Nkondo, Moses, undated (Box 4)
  - Faculty -- Paul-Emile, Barbara, undated; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Fellowships, 1975-1990 (Box 4)
  - Field trips, 1982-2003; (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Field work, 1977-1989; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Final examinations, undated (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation support material, undated (Box 4)
  - Ford Scholar program, circa 1989 (Box 8)
  - Forms - miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
  - Freshman advisees, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Freshman courses, undated (Box 4)
  - Freshman seminar, undated (Box 4)
  - Gay Lesbian Bisexual Task Force report, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Gospel choir, undated (Box 4)
  - Grants and fellowships, undated (Box 4)
  - Green Haven Prison, 1982-1983, undated; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Harassment Committee, undated (Box 4)
  - History Department, 1975-1981; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Independent major, undated (Box 4)
  - Interdepartmental correspondence, 1977-1979; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - International Studies, undated; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Kendrick House matter, 1975-1975 (Box 5)
  - Latin American Studies, undated (Box 5)
  - Library, 1973-1990; (17 folders) (Box 5)
  - Magazine articles and books, circa 1974-1982 (Box 5)
  - Mellon grant, undated (Box 5)
  - Middles States report, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Minorities in Higher Education, undated (Box 5)
  - Minority Freshman Orientation, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Multidisciplinary Program, undated; (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - National Congress of Black Faculty, undated; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - National Council of Black Studies, undated (Box 5)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, undated (Box 5)
  - New England Afro-American Studies Directors, undated (Box 5)
  - New England (building), 1974-1987; (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - New York State American-Black Studies Resource Survey, circa 1985-1988 (Box 5)
  - President, undated; (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - President and Trustee Committee on Minority Affairs, undated (Box 5)
  - Publicity, undated (Box 5)
  - Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, undated (Box 5)
  - Secretary, undated; (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Senior theses, 1990, undated (Box 5)
  - Sickle Cell Anemia Testing Program materials, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Sloan proposal, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Student employment and financial aid, 1977-1986 (Box 5)
  - Student forum, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Student honors and prizes, 1978-1988, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Student organizations, undated (Box 5)
  - Student organizations - Black Student Union, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Student organizations - Students' Afro-American Society, 1977-1988; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Study abroad, 1974-1991; (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - Study trip in Africa - Photographs, 1971; (2 albums and 2 packets) (Box 8)
  - Syllabi, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
  - Syllabi, 1981-1982, 1985-1986, 1997; (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Third World Festival, 1981-1993; (29 folders) (Box 6)
  - Third World Studies, undated (Box 6)
  - Urban Center, 1974-1981; (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Urban Studies, 1980-1986; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Vacancies, 1985-1988; (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Venture Consortium, undated (Box 6)
  - Women and the third world, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Women's Health Initiative, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Women's Studies, 1985-1989 (Box 6)
  - Work and Gender seminar, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
  - Zap Productions, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Zimand Fund, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Zimand Fund desegregation symposium, 1981 (Box 6)
- Series III. Lectures and Events
  - General files, 1975-2004; (17 folders) (Box 7)
  - Films, 1977-1987; (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Walter Rodney - Photographs, circa 1975 (Box 8)
  - Vinnie Burrows, 1978 Apr 12 (Box 7)
  - Ivan Van Sertima, 1978 Feb 16 (Box 7)
  - Michael Witter, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Micere Mugo, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Ronald Bailey, 1986 Feb 17 (Box 7)
  - John Callahan, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Black Jewish Relations panel, 1986 Feb 25 (Box 7)
  - Ebony Theatre Ensemble, 1987 Oct (Box 7)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. celebration, 1987 (Box 7)
  - June Jackson Christmas, 1988 Apr (Box 7)
  - Leonard Jeffries, Jr., 1988 (Box 7)
  - Calvin Butts, 1988 (Box 7)
  - 20th Anniversary, 1987-1989; (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Sylvia Boone, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Donald Bogle, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Muddathir Abdel Rahim, 1989 Apr 19 (Box 7)
  - President's Colloquium, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Leslie Collins, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Howard Dodson, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Eric Foner, 1989 (Box 7)
  - David L. Lewis, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Art Exhibition, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. celebration, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Symposium: Africana Studies in the Academy, 1989 Apr; (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. celebration, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - ASE Drumming Circle, circa 1990-1999 (Box 7)
  - Sudan Studies Association, 1992 Apr (Box 7)
  - Rex Nettleford, 1992 (Box 7)
  - 25th Anniversary, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Andrew Hacker, 1995 Feb (Box 7)
  - Margaret Walker, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Newark Boys Choir, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Louis Wilson, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Amistad event, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Michelle Wallace, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Proposed lecture series, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Hal Weaver, 1998 (Box 7)
  - A.J. Williams-Myers, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Retirement party for Norman Hodges, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Black History Month, 1999 (Box 7)
  - New York City Labor Chorus, 1999 Feb 6 (Box 7)
  - Paul Gilroy, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Alice Randall, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Taj Mahal, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Sudanic-Maghaaribi Studies Unit, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Michelle Cliff, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Sonia Sanchez, 2003 (Box 7)
  - Mohamed Ezroura, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Jazz festival, undated (Box 7)
- Series IV. Student and Personnel Records, [RESTRICTED]
  - Student Files, undated (Box 9)
  - Faculty Files, undated (Box 9)
  - Candidate files (to be weeded), undated (Boxes 10-11)